16. A thief in the night.
Now the days passed slowly and wearily.
Many of the dwarves spent their time piling and ordering the treasure, and
now Thoren spoke of the arkan stone of Thra, and bade them eagerly to look for
it in every corner. For the arkan stone of my father, he said, is worth more
than a river of gold in itself, and to me it is beyond price. That stone of all
the treasure I name unto myself, and I will be avenged on anyone who finds it
and withholds it. Do heard these words, and he grew afraid, wondering what would
happen if the stone was found wrapped in an old bundle of tattered oddments that
he used as a pillow. All the same, he did not speak of it, for as the
weariness of the days grew heavier, the beginnings of a plan had come into his
little head. Things had gone on like this for some time, when the ravens
brought news that Dne and more than 500 dwarves, hurrying from the iron hills,
were now within about 2 days march of Dale, coming from the northeast.
But they cannot reach the mountain unmarked, said Roach. And I fear lest
there be battle in the valley. I do not call this council good. Though they are
a grim folk, they are not likely to overcome the host that besets you. And
even if they did so, what will you gain?
Winter and snow is hastening behind them. How shall you be fed without the
friendship and goodwill of the lands about you? The treasure is likely to be
your death, though the dragon is no more. But Thoren was not moved. Winter
and snow will bite both men and elves, he said, and they may find their
dwelling in the waste grievous to bear.
With my friends behind them, and winter upon them, they will perhaps be in
softer mood to parley with. That night, Bilbo made up his mind. The sky was
black and moonless. As soon as it was full dark, he went to a corner of an
inner chamber just within the gate, and drew from his bundle a rope, and also
the arkan stone wrapped in a rag. Then he climbed to the top of the wall. Only
Bombore was there, for it was his turn to watch, and the dwarves kept only one
watchman at a time. "It is mighty cold," said Bomber. "I wish we could have a
fire up here, as they have in the camp."
"It is warm enough inside," said Bilbo.
"I dare say, but I am bound here till midnight," grumbled the fat dwarf. "A
sorry business altogether. Not that I venture to disagree with Thoren. May his
beard grow ever longer, yet he was ever a dwarf with a stiff neck. Not as stiff
as my legs, said Belo. I am tired of stairs and stone passages. I would give
a good deal for the feel of grass at my
toes. I would give a good deal for the feel of a strong drink in my throat, and
for a soft bed after a good supper. I can't give you those while the siege is
going on. But it is long since I watched, and I will take your turn for
you if you like. There is no sleep in me tonight. You are a good fellow, Mr.
Baggins, and I will take your offer kindly. If there should be anything to
note, rouse me first, mind you. I will lie in the inner chamber to the left,
not far away.
Off you go, said Bilbo. I will wake you at midnight and you can wake the next
watchman. As soon as Bour had gone, Bilbo put on his ring, fastened his
rope, slipped down over the wall, and was gone. He had about 5 hours before
him. Bomb would sleep. He could sleep at any time, and ever since the adventure
in the forest, he was always trying to recapture the beautiful dreams he had
then, and all the others were busy with Thoren. It was unlikely that any, even
Feelely or Killy, would come out on the wall until it was their turn. It was
very dark, and the road after a while, when he left the newly made path, and
climbed down towards the lower course of the stream, was strange to him. At last
he came to the bend, where he had to cross the water, if he was to make for
the camp, as he wished. The bed of the stream was there, shallow but already
broad, and folding it in the dark was not easy for the little hobbit. He was
nearly across when he missed his footing on a round stone, and fell into the cold
water with a splash. He had barely scrambled out on the far bank, shivering
and spluttering, when up came elves in the gloom with bright lanterns, and
searched for the cause of the noise.
"That was no fish," one said. "There is a spy about. Hide your lights. They will
help him more than us if it is that queer little creature that is said to be
their servant. Servant indeed, snorted Bobo, and in the middle of his snort, he
sneezed loudly, and the elves immediately gathered towards the sound.
Let's have a light, he said. I am here if you want me. And he slipped off his
ring and popped from behind a rock. They seized him quickly in spite of their
surprise. Poor you. Are you the dwarves habit? What are you doing? How did you
get so far past our sentinels? They asked one after another.
I am Mr. Bilbo Baggins, he answered.
Companion of Thoren, if you want to know. I know your king well by sight,
though perhaps he doesn't know me to look at. But Bard will remember me, and
it is Bard I particularly want to see.
Indeed, said they, and what may be your business. Whatever it is, it's my own,
my good elves. But if you wish ever to get back to your own woods from this
cold, cheerless place," he answered, shivering, "you will take me along quick
to a fire, where I can dry, and then you will let me speak to your chiefs as
quick as may be. I have only an hour or
two to spare." That is how it came about that some 2 hours after his escape from
the gate, Bilbo was sitting beside a warm fire in front of a large tent, and
there sat too, gazing curiously at him, both the elven king and bard. A hobbit
and Elvish armor, partly wrapped in an old blanket, was something new to them.
"Really? You know," Bilbo was saying in his best business manner, "Things are
impossible. Personally, I am tired of the whole affair. I wish I was back in
the west in my own home, where folk are more reasonable. But I have an interest
in this matter one4th share, to be precise, according to a letter, which
fortunately I believe I have kept. He drew from a pocket in his old jacket,
which he still wore over his mail, crumpled and much folded, Thoren's
letter that had been put under the clock on his mantelpiece in May. a share in
the profits. Mind you, he went on, I am aware of that. Personally, I am only too
ready to consider all your claims carefully and deduct what is right from
the total before putting in my own claim.
However, you don't know Thor and Oaken Shield as well as I do now. I assure
you, he is quite ready to sit on a heap
of gold and starve as long as you sit here." "Well, let him," said Bard. Such
a fool deserves to starve.
Quite so, said Bilbo. I see your point of view. At the same time, winter is
coming on fast. Before long, you will be having snow and whatn not, and supplies
will be difficult even for elves, I imagine. Also, there will be other
difficulties. You have not heard of Dne and the dwarves of the Iron Hills. We
have a long time ago. But what has he got to do with us? asked the king. I
thought as much. I see I have some information you have not got. Dne, I may
tell you, is now less than 2 days march off, and has at least 500 grim dwarves
with him. A good many of them have had experience in the dreadful dwarf and
goblin wars, of which you have no doubt heard. When they arrive, there may be
serious trouble. Why do you tell us this? Are you betraying your friends, or
are you threatening us? asked Bard grimly.
My dear Bard, squeaked Bilbo. Don't be so hasty. I never met such suspicious
folk. I am merely trying to avoid trouble for all concerned. Now I will
make you an offer. Let us hear it, they said. You may see it, said he. It is
this, and he drew forth the arkan stone and threw away the wrapping. The elven
king himself, whose eyes were used to things of wonder and beauty, stood up in
amazement. Even Bard gazed, marveling at it in silence. It was as if a globe had
been filled with moonlight and hung before them in a net woven of the glint
of frosty stars. "This is the ark and stone of terrain," said Bilbo, "the
heart of the mountain, and it is also the heart of Thoren. He values it above
a river of gold. I give it to you. It will aid you in your bargaining. Then
Bilbo, not without a shudder, not without a glance of longing, handed the
marvelous stone to Bard, and he held it in his hand as though dazed, "but how is
it yours to give?" he asked at last with an effort. "Oh well," said the hobbit
uncomfortably, "it isn't exactly, but well, I am willing to let it stand
against all my claim, don't you know? I may be a burglar, or so they say.
Personally, I never really felt like one, but I am an honest one. I hope more
or less. Anyway, I am going back now, and the dwarves can do what they like to
me. I hope you will find it useful. The elven king looked at Bilbo with a new
wander. Bilbo Baggins. He said, "You are more worthy to wear the armor
of elf princes than many that have looked more calmly in it.
But I wonder if Thor and Oaken Shield will see it so. I have more knowledge of
dwarves in general than you have perhaps. I advise you to remain with us,
and here you shall be honored and thrice welcome." "Thank you very much. I am
sure," said Belbo with a bow. But I don't think I ought to leave my friends
like this after all we have gone through together. And I promise to wake old
Bomber at midnight, too. Really, I must be going, and quickly.
Nothing they could say would stop him, so an escort was provided for him, and
as he went, both the king and bard saluted him with honor. As they passed
through the camp, an old man wrapped in a dark cloak rose from a tent door where
he was sitting and came towards them.
Well done, Mr. Baggins," he said, clapping Bilbo on the back. "There is
always more about you than anyone expects." It was Gandalf.
For the first time for many a day, Bilbo was really delighted, but there was no
time for all the questions that he immediately wished to ask. "All in good
time," said Gandalf. "Things are drawing towards the end now, unless I am
mistaken. There is an unpleasant time just in front of you, but keep your
heart up. You may come through all right. There is news brewing that even
the ravens have not heard. Good night.
Puzzled but cheered, Bilbo hurried on.
He was guided to a safe ford and set across dry, and then he said farewell to
the elves and climbed carefully back towards the gate. Great weariness began
to come over him, but it was well before midnight when he clambored up the rope
again. it, and then he sat down on the wall and wondered anxiously what would
happen next. He untied it and hid it, and then he sat down on the wall and
wondered anxiously what would happen next. At midnight he woke up on Boore,
and then in turn rolled himself up in his corner without listening to the old
dwarf's thanks, which he felt he had hardly earned. He was soon fast asleep,
forgetting all his worries till the morning. As a matter of fact, he was
dreaming of eggs and bacon. Chapter 17.